{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The city of Bagram was originally the capital of an ethnically Greek state that practiced this\nreligion. Two statues of this religion's founder at Bamiyan (pr. BAY-mee-yahn) were destroyed\nby the Taliban. For 10 points, name this religion whose Vajryana (pr. VAHJ-rye-AH-nuh) form\nis practiced in Tibet by followers of the Dalai Lama.",
      "answer": "Buddhism"
    },
    {
      "question": "Near the end of his life, this man gave a speech identifying the \"three boxes\" as the source of\nrights. This man was nominated for Vice-President by the Equal Rights Party on the Victoria\nWoodhull ticket. This orator gave a speech asking \"what, to the slave, is the Fourth of July\" after\nfounding The North Star. This author of My Bondage and My Freedom wrote about his escape\nfrom Mr. Covey in Maryland. For 10 points, name this former slave turned abolitionist.",
      "answer": "Frederick Douglass, Douglass"
    },
    {
      "question": "Along with Henry David Thoreau, this thinker was cited as the chief Western influence on\nGandhi. His pacifist tome The Kingdom of God is Within You made him the leader of dissenting\nChristians in early twentieth century Russia. For 10 points, name this man who viewed his\ntheological work as more important than his novels, such as Anna Karenina",
      "answer": "Leo Tolstoy, Tolstoy, Lev Nikolayevich Tolstoy"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was set in motion when Abel Corbin introduced its two plotters to the President,\nand Daniel Butterfield agreed to pass along inside information. This 1869 event tainted the Grant\nadministration and was an attempt by James Fisk and Jay Gould to \"corner\" the gold market. For\n10 points, identify this day, which shares its name with a post-Thanksgiving shopping event.",
      "answer": "Black Friday"
    },
    {
      "question": "This king ordered the destruction of all remaining Protestant churches in the Edict of\nFontainebleau (pr. FAHN-tohn-blow). He was opposed at his accession by the Fronde\nmovement, which was countered by his early advisor, Cardinal Mazarin. For 10 points, name this\nmonarch who reigned for seventy-two years as the absolutist \"Sun King\" of France.",
      "answer": "Louis XIV"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man headed the Firebird and GTO projects while he was chief engineer of Pontiac, prior\nto starting his own namesake company. In 1982, he was arrested for participating in a cocaine\ndeal, which he was acquitted of at trial after arguing entrapment. For 10 points, identify this man\nwhose car firm produced a gull-winged, unpainted steel car used in Back to the Future.",
      "answer": "John DeLorean, DeLorean"
    },
    {
      "question": "This party was victimized by the Zinoviev letter hoax, which purported to show Soviet control\nof its operations and brought down its first prime minister, Ramsay Macdonald. This party was\nfirst represented in Parliament by Scottish coal miner Keir Hardie. For 10 points, name this\nparty, now the more left-wing of the two largest political parties in the United Kingdom.",
      "answer": "Labour Party, Labour"
    },
    {
      "question": "Zacharias Janssen may have invented the first version of this device, which was first used in\nbiology by Anton van Leeuwenhoek (pr. LAY-ven-hoke). In 1932, Ernst Ruska pioneered the\n\"electron\" type of this device, which was used to discover cells in cork by Robert Hooke. For 10\npoints, identify this device which lens-grinders created to peer at tiny objects.",
      "answer": "microscope"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's prominent depiction on the cover of When the Word Is Given offended his\nsuperiors, as did his commentary that the John F. Kennedy assassination was \"a case of chickens\ncoming home to roost.\" He was killed at the Audubon Ballroom, most likely by agents of Elijah\nMuhammad. For 10 points, name this chief spokesman for the Nation of Islam.",
      "answer": "Malcom X, Malcolm Little, Little"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the autumn of 1649, this man led armies which sacked Drogheda (pr. DRAH-huh-dah),\nleading to his reputation as a cruel conqueror of Ireland. He was succeeded by his son Richard\nafter his death. For 10 points, name this leader of the New Model Army who attained supreme\npower as \"Lord Protector of England\" after the Civil War.",
      "answer": "Oliver Cromwell, Cromwell"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS EXAMPLE) What President of Germany, who appointed Hitler Chancellor in 1933, was the\nnamesake of a zeppelin that caught fire above New Jersey in 1937?",
      "answer": "Paul von Hindenburg, Hindenburg"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The \"foundations\" of this field were described in a book by David Hilbert, and its \"hyperbolic\"\nform was pioneered by János Bolyai (pr. YAH-nowsh BOWL-yai) and the Russian Nikolai\nLobachevsky (pr. LOH-buh-CHEFF-skee). For 10 points, name this math field whose\nfoundational text is the Elements by Euclid (pr. YOOK-lid), which discusses the parallel\npostulate and Pythagorean theorem.",
        "answer": "geometry"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other kind of mathematics was invented simultaneously by Gottfried Leibniz and\nIsaac Newton, who long quarreled over the credit for its discovery?",
        "answer": "calculus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This artist depicted Nazi concentration camp victims in The Charnel House. In the late 1940s,\nthis wealthy artist was the primary financial backer of the French Communist Party. An earlier\npolitical painting by him shows a lightbulb, a horse, and a screaming woman in memory of a\nBasque village bombed by the Nazis. For 10 points, name this creator of Guernica.",
        "answer": "Pablo Picasso, Picasso, Pablo Ruiz y Picasso"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "World War II itself caused the disappearance of many artworks, such as the Amber\nRoom formerly found in what city, which was besieged by Nazis for nine hundred days?",
        "answer": "St. Petersburg, Leningrad"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s former troops revolted against it in the Mercenary War. As a result, this city's\nleader Hanno the Great was displaced by the rising Barcid dynasty, whose members included\nHamilcar and Hasdrubal. This city lost the Battle of Zama to Scipio Africanus. For 10 points\nname this ancient North African city which was defeated by Rome in three Punic Wars.",
        "answer": "Carthage"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The site of Carthage is in which present day African country, whose soccer team is\nthus known as the Carthage Eagles?",
        "answer": "Tunisia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the 1950s, this team was led by quarterback Y.A. Tittle and the \"Million Dollar Backfield.\"\nThis team's receiver Dwight Clark made \"The Catch\" in 1982, and in January 1995, with\nquarterback Steve Young, they became the first NFL team to win a fifth Super Bowl. For 10\npoints, name this team that won four titles under the leadership of Joe Montana.",
        "answer": "San Francisco 49ers, San Francisco, 49ers"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 1950s, this team was led by quarterback Y.A. Tittle and the \"Million Dollar Backfield.\"\nThis team's receiver Dwight Clark made \"The Catch\" in 1982, and in January 1995, with\nquarterback Steve Young, they became the first NFL team to win a fifth Super Bowl. For 10\npoints, name this team that won four titles under the leadership of Joe Montana.",
        "answer": "Jerry Rice, Rice"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Soon after independence, this country fell under the domination of the \"hairy feet\" secret\npolice of José de Francia. This country was ruled by the eccentric Francisco Solano Lopez when\nit lost the majority of its male population to the War of the Triple Alliance. For 10 points,\nidentify this country which has developed oddly due to its landlocked position in South America.",
        "answer": "Paraguay, Republic of Paraguay, Republica del Paraguay"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The War of the Triple Alliance proved a victory for Pedro II, a member of the\nBraganza Dynasty and the last person to hold what imperial title?",
        "answer": "Emperor of Brazil"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A powerful official in this government was the \"censor,\" who determined eligibility for the\nSenate. Politicians under this government followed the \"cursus honorum\" to move through the\nranks of aedile (pr. EY-dial), quaestor (pr. KWAI-stor), praetor (pr. PRAI-tor), and finally\nbecome one of two consuls. For 10 points, name this governmental system which was replaced\nby the Empire.",
        "answer": "Roman Republic, Republic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A legendary censor was the \"elder\" man of what name, who was also known for ending\nhis speeches in the Senate by declaring \"Carthage must be destroyed?\"",
        "answer": "Cato"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A bronze age museum is maintained at a \"crannog\" in County Clare on this island. This island\nregained its independence from Viking kingdoms at the 1014 Battle of Clontarf, re-establishing\nthe High King's seat at the hill of Tara. The Book of Kells can be seen at Trinity College Library\non this island. For 10 points, name this island, also home to the James Joyce Museum in Dublin.",
        "answer": "Ireland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What city in southwest Ireland is the namesake of a humorous poetic form?",
        "answer": "Limerick"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A desire to control this site sparked a brief 1860s war between France and Siam. This complex\nwas built by Suryavarman II (pr. SIR-yuh-VAHR-mun the second) in the early twelfth century\nand dedicated to Vishnu, though it was later used for Buddhist worship. For 10 points, identify\nthis Khmer (pr. kuh-MARE) Kingdom temple complex, or \"wat,\" in what is now Cambodia.",
        "answer": "Angkor Wat, Angkor"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Cambodia later came under the rule of the Khmer Rouge, a Communist movement led\nby what dictator whose original name was Saloth Sar?",
        "answer": "Pol Pot"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "RECONSTRUCTION",
      "prompt": "During the post-Civil War Reconstruction period in the U.S., who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State that took a long time to recover from Sherman’s March from Atlanta to Savannah?",
          "answer": "Georgia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hood-wearing group of Southern vigilantes which violently opposed black political power?",
          "answer": "KKK, Ku Klux Klan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Derogatory term given by Southerners to Northerners who moved South?",
          "answer": "carpetbaggers, carpetbagger"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who was impeached during the Reconstruction Era?",
          "answer": "Andrew Johnson, A Johnson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Constitutional amendment which prohibited slavery throughout the United States?",
          "answer": "Thirteenth Amendment, Thirteenth"
        },
        {
          "question": "Two-word name given to the dominant faction in Congress which drove Reconstruction?",
          "answer": "Radical Republicans, Radical Republican"
        },
        {
          "question": "Long-unenforced Constitutional amendment barring racial discrimination in voting?",
          "answer": "Fifteenth Amendment, Fifteenth"
        },
        {
          "question": "President whose inauguration ended Reconstruction as part of the Compromise of 1877?",
          "answer": "Rutherford B. Hayes, Hayes, Rutherford Birchard Hayes"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CHARLEMAGNE",
      "prompt": "Medieval emperor Charlemagne...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was crowned on Christmas 800 by Leo III, a holder of what top office of the Catholic\nChurch?",
          "answer": "Pope, the Papacy, Papacy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Instigated the \"Carolingian\" example of what sort of period in which arts and learning revive?",
          "answer": "renaissance"
        },
        {
          "question": "Launched a crusade against what Germanic people, who earlier joined with the Angles to\nconquer England?",
          "answer": "Saxons, Saxon"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 797, took control of what currently second largest city in Spain?",
          "answer": "Barcelona"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the son of what small-statured king?",
          "answer": "Pepin the Short, Pepin III, Pepin le Bref, Pippin der Kurze"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was gifted what kind of large animal, known as Abul-Abbas, by the Abbasid caliph?",
          "answer": "elephant"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the leader of which Germanic tribe who were earlier led by the Merovingians?",
          "answer": "Franks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the grandson of what Mayor of the Palace who won the Battle of Tours?",
          "answer": "Charles Martel, Carolus Martellus, Karl Martell"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE PHILIPPINES",
      "prompt": "The present-day country of the Philippines is or was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Colonized by what European power, after whose king Philip II it was named?",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Controlled from an 1898 war until independence by what country?",
          "answer": "United States of America, USA, America"
        },
        {
          "question": "Home to the Moro people and Abu Sayyaf (pr. sai-AHF) movement, which follow what\nminority religion?",
          "answer": "Sunni Islam, Muslim, Muslims"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of the Battle of Leyte (pr. LAY-tee) Gulf during which war?",
          "answer": "World War II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Subject to the “New Society” regime of what dictator from 1965 to 1986?",
          "answer": "Ferdinand Marcos"
        },
        {
          "question": "Home to thousands of what item of clothing that belonged to that man's wife Imelda?",
          "answer": "shoes"
        },
        {
          "question": "The destination of galleons that left the port of Acapulco from which country in the Americas?",
          "answer": "Mexico"
        },
        {
          "question": "Briefly led as president by what independence activist who led an anti-American insurgency\nuntil 1901?",
          "answer": "Emilio Aguinaldo, Aguinaldo"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Buffalo Springfield insisted that the song \"For What It's Worth\" was about the Sunset Strip curfew riots and not this event. This event was the subject of Country Joe and the Fish's biggest hit. A veteran of this conflict is the subject of (20 pts) ",
        "Bruce Springsteen's \"Born in the USA,\" and a (10 pts) ",
        "protest against this conflict inspired Neil Young to write \"Ohio\" about the Kent State shootings. For 10 points, name this war which inspired copious protest music in the late 1960s."
      ],
      "answer": "Vietnam War, Vietnam"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1844, the U.S. dispatched missionary Peter Parker and attorney Caleb Cushing to this country to negotiate a trade pact. This country signed the 1868 Burlingame Treaty with the United States. This country's natives were the subject of the (20 pts) ",
        "Geary Act, and were prohibited from entering the U.S. between 1882 and 1943 under a namesake (10 pts) ",
        "\"Exclusion Act.\" For 10 points, name this country which is now, after Canada, the second-largest trade partner of the U.S."
      ],
      "answer": "China, People's Republic of China"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An important 1878 piece for this instrument was composed for the virtuoso Joseph Joachim (pr. YO-zef YO-ah-keem). This instrument was played by a composer of (20 pts) ",
        "twenty-four caprices who allegedly made a deal with the devil, Niccolò (10 pts) ",
        "Paganini. Many valuable examples of this instrument were created by the master craftsman Antonio Stradivari. For 10 points, name this string instrument which an orchestra's concertmaster plays."
      ],
      "answer": "violin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This organization was formed at the suggestion of Mary White Ovington following the Springfield riot of 1908, and it absorbed many veterans of the Niagara Movement. This organization awards the (20 pts) ",
        "Spingarn Medals, and its first major effort was publishing The Crisis under the editorship of (10 pts) ",
        "W.E.B. DuBois (pr. doo-BOYZ). For 10 points, name this organization which led the anti-segregationist movement for much of the twentieth century."
      ],
      "answer": "NAACP, National Association for the Advancement of Colored People"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man won a Nobel Prize in Literature for his History of the English-Speaking Peoples. This man was First Lord of the Admiralty during the (20 pts) ",
        "Gallipoli disaster, though his \"wilderness years\" eventually ended and allowed him to make the \"we shall (10 pts) ",
        "fight them on the beaches\" speech. He was defeated in his first re-election bid by Clement Attlee. For 10 points, name this leader of the national unity government of the U.K. during World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Winston Churchill, Churchill"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this organization were represented in the Reichstag by the Centre Party. This organization was targeted by Adalbert von Falk's May Laws, part of the (20 pts) ",
        "Kulturkampf (pr. KOOL-tur-kompf) against it launched by Otto von Bismarck. A leader of this organization who was accused of turning a blind eye to the Holocaust was (10 pts) ",
        "Pius XII. For 10 points, name this organization which is the predominant Christian denomination in southern Germany."
      ],
      "answer": "Roman Catholic Church, Catholic"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) People who opposed this action wrote under the pen names Cato, Brutus, and the Federal Farmer, and were most likely George Clinton, Robert Yates, and Mercy Otis Warren. This action was supported in a series of (20 pts) ",
        "letters to the New York Packet written by \"Publius,\" a collective pseudonym for James (10 pts) ",
        "Madison, John Jay, and Alexander Hamilton. For 10 points, what was this action which was advocated in the Federalist Papers and created the present U.S. government?"
      ],
      "answer": "ratifying the U.S. Constitution, ratifying Constitution"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first-ever U.S. Cabinet member to serve a prison sentence did so as a result of this scandal. This scandal's investigation by Thomas Walsh led to the Supreme Court case of McGrain v. Daugherty, which held that Congress may require people to testify. It involved (20 pts) ",
        "land in the Black Hills which Albert Fall, the Secretary of the Interior, leased to (10 pts) ",
        "oil prospectors at cut rates. For 10 points, identify this defining scandal of the Warren Harding administration."
      ],
      "answer": "Teapot Dome"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This city was the site of a Church council held five years before the Council of Constance which elected Alexander V as Pope in an attempt to end the Western Schism. This city was the loser of the Battle of (20 pts) ",
        "Meloria, and it was where a man allegedly dropped (10 pts) ",
        "cannonballs out of a window in order to measure acceleration. For 10 points, name this home to a gravitational experiment by Galileo, who made use of an architectural blunder that created its \"leaning tower.\""
      ],
      "answer": "Pisa"
    }
  ]
}